[Music]
Reedman
reads The Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser rean chapter
[Music]
13 Days went by, and weeks. Jonas learned, through the memories, the names of
colors; and now he began to see them all, in his ordinary life (though he knew it
was ordinary no longer it would never be again). But they didn't last. There would
be a glimpse of green— —the landscaped lawn around the Central Plaza; a bush on
the River Bank The bright orange of pumpkins being trucked in from the
agricultural fields beyond the community boundary— —seen in an instant, the flash of
brilliant color, but gone again, returning to their flat and Hess shade.
The Giver told him that it would be a very long time before he had the colors to
keep. "But I want them!" Jonas said angrily.
"It isn't fair that nothing has color!" "Not fair?" The Giver looked at Jonas
curiously. "Explain what you mean." "Well..." ..."Jonas had to stop and think it
through. "If everything's the same, then there aren't any choices! I want to wake
up in the morning and decide things! A blue tunic, or a red
one?" He looked down at himself, at the colorless fabric of his
clothing. "But it's all the same, always."
Then he laughed a little. "I know it's not important, what you wear. It doesn't matter.
But—" "It's the choosing that's important, isn't it?" The Giver asked him. Jonas
nodded. "My little brother—" he began, and then corrected himself.
"No, that's not accurate He's not my brother, not really. But this new child that my family
takes care of— —his name's Gabriel?" "Yes, I know about
Gabriel." "Well, he's right at the age where he's learning so much. He grabs toys when
we would hold them in front of him— —my father says he's learning small muscle
control. And he's really cute we give her nodded. "But now that I
can see colors, at least sometimes, I was just thinking: what if we could hold up things that
were bright red, or bright yellow, and he could choose? Instead of the
Sameness." "He might make wrong choices." "Oh." Jonas was silent for a
minute. "Oh, I I see what you mean. It wouldn't matter for a new
child's toy. But later it does matter, doesn't it? We don't dare to let people
make choices of their own." "Not safe?" The Giver suggested. "Definitely not safe Jonah said
with certainty. "What if they were allowed to choose their own mate? And chose
wrong? "Or what if," he went on, almost laughing at the absurdity, "they chose their own
jobs? "Frightening, isn't it?" The Giver said. Jonas chuckled. "Very frightening. I
can't even imagine it. We really have to protect people from wrong choices." "It's
safer." "Yes," Jonas agreed. "Much safer when the conversation turned to
other things, Jonas was left, still, with a feeling of frustration that he didn't
understand. He found that he was often angry, now: irrationally angry at his
groupmates, that they were satisfied with their lives which had none of the
vibrance his own was taking on. And he was angry at himself, that he could not
change that for them. He tried.
Without asking permission from The Giver, because he feared— —or knew— —that it would
be denied, he tried to give his new awareness to his friends. "Asher Jonah said one morning,
"look at those flowers very carefully."
They were standing beside a bed of geraniums planted near the Hall of Open
Records. He put his hands on Asher's shoulders, and concentrated on the red of
the petals, trying to hold it as long as he could, and trying at the same time to
transmit the awareness of red to his friend. "What's the matter?" Asher asked
uneasily. "Is something wrong it moved away from Jonas's hands. It was extremely rude for one
citizen to touch another outside of family units. "No, nothing. I thought for a
minute that they were wilting, and we should let the Gardening Crew know that
they needed more watering." Jonas side and turned
away. One evening he came home from his training waited with new
knowledge. The Giver had chosen a startling and disturbing memory that day.
Under the touch of his hands, Jonas had found himself suddenly in a place that
was completely alien: hot and windswept under a vast blue sky. There were toughs
of sparse grass, a few bushes and rocks, and nearby he could see an area of
thicker vegetation: broad, low trees outlined against the sky. He could hear
noises: the sharp crack of weapons— —he perceived the word guns —and then shouts,
and an immense crashing thud as something fell, tearing branches from the
trees. He heard voices calling to one another. Peering from the place where he
stood hidden behind some shrubbery, he was reminded of what The Giver had told
him, that there had been a time when flesh had different
colors. Two of these men had dark brown skin; the others were light.
Going closer, he watched them hack the tusks from a motionless elephant on the
ground and haul them away, spattered with blood. He felt himself overwhelmed with a
new perception of the color he knew as red. Then the men were gone, speeding
toward the horizon in a vehicle that spit pebbles from its whirling
tires. One hit his forehead and stung him there. But the memory continued, though
Jonas achd now for it to end.
Now we saw another elephant emerge from the place where it had stood hidden in the
trees. Very slowly it walked to the mutilated body and looked
down. With its sinuous trunk it stroked the huge corpse; then it reached up, broke some
leafy branches with a snap, and draped them over the mass of torn thick
flesh. Finally it tilted its massive head, raised its trunk, and roared into the empty
landscape. Jonas had never heard such a sound. It was a sound of rage and grief
and it never seemed to end. He could still hear it when he
opened his eyes and lay anguished on the bed where he received the
memories continued to roar into his consciousness as he pedal slowly
home. "Lily," he asked that evening when his sister took her comfort object, the
stuffed elephant, from the shelf, "did you know that once there really were elephants? Live
ones?" She glanced down at the ragged comfort object and grinned. "Right," she
said, skeptically. "Sure, Jonas." Jonas went and sat beside them
while his father untied Lily's hair ribbons and combed her
hair. He placed one hand on each of their shoulders. With all of his being he tried
to give each of them a piece of the memory: not of the tortured cry of the elephant,
but of the being of the elephant, of the towering, immense creature and the
meticulous touch with which it attended its friend at the
end. But his father had continued to comb Lily's long hair, and Lily, impatient, had
finally wiggled under her brother's touch. "Jonas," she said, "you're hurting me with your
hand." "I apologize for hurting you, Lily," Jonas mumbled, and took his hand away
accept your apology," Lily responded indifferently, stroking the lifeless
elephant. "Giver," Jonas asked once, as they prepared for the day's work, "don't you
have a spouse? Aren't you allowed to apply for one?" Although he was exempted
from the rules against rudeness, he was aware that this was a rude question. But
The Giver had encouraged all of his questions, not seeming to be embarrassed
or offended by even the most personal. The Giver chuckled. "No, there's
no rule against it. And I did have a spouse. You're forgetting how old I am,
Jonas. My former spouse lives now with the Childless Adults." "Oh, of
course." Jonas had forgotten The Giver's obvious age. When adults of the community became
older, their lives became different. They were no longer needed to create family
units. Jonas's own parents, when he and Lily were grown, would have to go live
with the Childless Adults.
"You'll be able to apply for a spouse, Jonas, if you want to. I'll warn you,
though, that it will be difficult. Your living arrangements will
have to be different from those of most family units, because the books are forbidden to
citizens. You and I are the only ones with access to the books." Jonas glanced around at the
astonishing array of volumes. From time to time, now, he could see their
colors. With their hours together, his and The givers consumed by conversation and
by the transmission of memories, Jonas had not yet opened any of the books. But
he read the titles here and there, and knew that they contained all of the
knowledge of centuries, and that one day they would belong to
him. "So if I have a spouse, and maybe children, I will have to hide the books from
them Giver nodded. "I wasn't permitted to share the books with with my spouse, that's
correct there are other difficulties, too.
You remember the rule that says the new Receiver can't talk about his
training?" Jonas nodded. Of course he remembered. It had turned out, by far, to
be the most frustrating of the rules he was required to obey. "When you become the
official Receiver, when we're finished here, you'll be given a whole new set of
rules. Those are the rules that I obey.
And it won't surprise you that I am forbidden to talk about my work to
anyone except the new Receiver. That's you, of course. "So there will be a whole
part of your life which you won't be able to share with your family. It's hard,
Jonas. It was hard for me. "You do understand, don't you, that this is my life? The
memories?" Jonas nodded again, but he was puzzled. Didn't life consist of the
things you did each day? There wasn't anything else, really.
"I've seen you taking walks," he said. The Giver sighed. "I walk. I eat at
meal time when I am called by the Committee of Elders, I appear before them,
to give them counsel and advice." "Do you advise them often?" Jonas
was a little frightened at the thought that one day he would be the one to
advise the ruling body. But The Giver said no. "Rarely. Only when they're faced with
something they have not experienced before. Then they call upon me to use the
memories and advise them. But it very seldom happens. Sometimes I wish they'd ask for
my wisdom more often— —there are so many things I could tell them; things I wish they would
change. But they don't want change. Life here is so orderly, so
predictable— —so painless is what they've chosen." "I don't know why they even need a
Receiver and if they never call upon him," Jonas commented. "They need me. And you," The
Giver said, but didn't explain. "They were reminded of that 10 years ago." "What
happened 10 years ago?" Jonas asked. "Oh, I know. You tried to train a successor and it
failed. Why? Why did that remind them?" The Giver smiled
grimly. "When the new Receiver failed, the memories that she had received were
released. They didn't come back to me.
They went and paused, and seemed to be struggling with the
concept. "I don't know, exactly. They went to the place where memories once existed
before Receivers were created. Someplace out there He gestured vaguely with his
arm. "And then the people had access to them. Apparently that's the way it was,
once. Everyone had access to memories.
"It was chaos," he said. "They really suffered for a while. Finally it subsided as the
memories were assimilated. But it certainly made them aware of how they
need a Receiver to contain all that pain.
And knowledge." "But you have to suffer like that all the time," Jonas pointed out. The Giver
nodded. "And you will. It's my life. It will be yours Jon has thought about it, about
what it would be like for him. "Along with walking and eating and—" He
looked around the walls of books. "Reading?
That's it?" The Giver shook his head. "Those are simply the things that I do. My life
is here." "In this room?" The Giver shook his head put his hands to his own face, to
his chest. "No. Here, in my being. Where the memories are." "My Instructors in science and
technology have taught us about how the brain works," Jonas told him eagerly. "It's
full of electrical impulses. It's like a computer. If you stimulate one part of
the brain with an electrode, it—" He stopped talking. He could see an odd look on The Giver's
face. "They know nothing," The Giver said bitterly. Jonas was shocked.
Since the first day in the Annex room, they had together disregarded the rules
about rudess and Jonas felt comfortable with that now this was different far beyond
rude. This was a terrible accusation. What if someone had heard? He quickly glanced
at the wall speaker, terrified that the Committee might be listening as they could at any
time. But, as always during their sessions together, the switch had been turned to
OFF. "Nothing?" Jonas whispered nervously. "But my instructors—" The Giver flicked his hand
as if brushing something aside all your instructors were well trained. They know
their scientific facts. Everyone is well trained for his
job. "It's just that without the memories it's all meaningless. They gave that
burden to me. And to the previous Receiver. And the one before
him." "And back back and back Jonah said, knowing the phrase that always came. The
Giver smiled, though his smile was oddly harsh. "That's right. And next it will be you. A great
honor." "Yes, sir. They told me that at the Ceremony. The very highest
honor." Some afternoons The Giver sent him away without
training. Jonas knew, on day days when he arrived to find The Giver hunched over,
rocking his body slightly back and forth, his face pale, that he would be sent
away. "Go," The Giver would tell him tensely.
"I'm in pain today. Come back tomorrow." On those days, worried and
disappointed, Jonas would walk alone beside the river. The paths were empty of
people except for the few Delivery Crews and Landscape Workers here and there.
Small children were all at the child care Center after after school, and the
older ones busy with volunteer hours of training. By himself, he tested his own developing
memory. He watched the landscape for glimpses of the green that he knew was embedded in the
shrubbery; when it came flickering into his consciousness, he focused upon it,
keeping it there, darkening it, holding it in his vision as long as possible until
his head hurt and he let it fade away. He stared at the flat, colorless sky,
bringing blue from it he remembered sunshine until finally, for an instant, he could feel
warmth. He stood at the foot of the bridge that spanned the river, the bridge
that citizens were allowed to cross only on official business. Jonas had crossed
it on school trips, visiting the outling communities, and he knew that the land
beyond the bridge was much the same, flat and well ordered, with fields for
agriculture. The other communities he had seen on visits were essentially the same
as his own, the only differences were slightly altered styles of dwellings,
slightly different schedules in the schools. He wondered what lay in the far
distance where he had never gone. The land didn't end beyond those nearby
communities. Were there hills Elsewhere?
Were there vast wind torn areas like the place he had seen in memory, the place
where the elephant
died? "Giver," he asked one after afternoon following a day when he had been sent
away, "what causes you pain?" When The Giver was silent, Jonas
continued. "The Chief Elder told me, at the beginning, that the receiving of memory
causes terrible pain. And you describ for me that the failure of the last new Receiver
released painful memories to the community. "But I haven't suffered, Giver.
Not really Jonah smiled well I remember the sunburn you gave me on the the very
first day. But that wasn't so terrible. What is it that makes you
suffer so much? If you gave some of it to me, maybe your pain would be
less." The Giver nodded. "Lie down," he said. "It's time, I suppose. I can't shield you
forever we'll have to take it all on eventually. "Let me think," he went on, when
Jonas was was on the bed, waiting, a little fearful. "All right," The Giver said after a
moment, "I've decided. We'll start with something familiar. Let's go once again to a hill, and a
sled." He placed his hands on Jonas's back
[Music]